Guide to the VERSEtility BOOKS Records
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
VERSEtility BOOKS records
1985-2001
YCAL MSS 700
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
5.05
(7 boxes)
The VERSEtility BOOKS Records consist of correspondence, financial papers, computer disks, and other administrative files relating to the bookselling business of VERSEtility BOOKS. Correspondence contains letters between Jacob and poets regarding their signed books and subsequent sales. A small portion of the correspondence relates to the appraisal and sale of poets' personal libraries to various universities. Financial papers and administrative files include sales records, bills, invoices, and correspondence regarding the financial operation of the business. Nine computer disks store VERSEtility BOOKS catalogs and advertisements for Poetry Magazine.
VERSEtility BOOKS
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Purchased from Robert Jacob on the Eugene G. O'Neill Memorial Fund, 2002.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Box 7 (computer disks): Restricted fragile material. Reference copies of electronic files may be requested. Consult Access Services for further information.
VERSEtility BOOKS
VERSEtility BOOKS was a book selling business founded by Bob Jacob in Connecticut. Prior to its founding, Jacob and his wife, Betty Jacob, owned Brook Farm Inn in Lenox, Massachusetts, an inn they dedicated to poetry by housing poets free of charge and hosting poetry events. In 1992, they sold the farm and moved to Connecticut. VERSEtility BOOKS's mission was the sale of signed copies of poets' books and donation of most profits to the poets. Through relationships with a few poets, Jacob was asked to appraise their private book collections and broker sales of these collections to universities. VERSEtility BOOKS ceased operation in 2001 and Jacob turned his attention to reading poetry to cancer support groups and volunteering his time at the Connecticut Hospice Hospital in Branford and other hospitals.
Scope and Contents
The VERSEtility BOOKS Records consist of correspondence, financial papers, computer disks, and other administrative files relating to the bookselling business of VERSEtility BOOKS. Correspondence contains letters between Jacob and poets regarding their signed books and subsequent sales. A small portion of the correspondence relates to the appraisal and sale of poets' personal libraries to various universities. Financial papers and administrative files include sales records, bills, invoices, and correspondence regarding the financial operation of the business. Nine computer disks store VERSEtility BOOKS catalogs and advertisements for Poetry Magazine.
Arrangement
Organized into two groupings: I. May 2002 Acquisitions, 1985-2001. II. October 2002 Acquisition, 1986-2001.
Poetry (Chicago, Ill.); American poetry -- 20th Century; Poets, American -- 20th Century; Born digital; Poets -- United States -- 20th Century; Jacob, Betty; Jacob, Bob, 1932-; VERSEtility BOOKS
- May 2002 Acquisitions, 1985-2001; 1; 1.84; (3 boxes)
  Scope and Contents
  Consists of correspondence with various poets regarding the signing and sale of their books and checks made out to various poets.
  Former call number: Uncat MSS 291
  Arrangement
  Correspondence grouped into two alphabetical runs.
  - Correspondence
    - Ai, 1993-1994, 1998 (Box 1)
    - Atwood, Margaret, 1993 (Box 1)
    - Berrigan, Daniel, undated (Box 1)
    - Bell, Marvin, 1993 (Box 1)
    - Berry, Wendell, 1993 (Box 1)
    - Blumenthal, Michael C., 1989, 1990s (Box 1)
    - Bly, Robert, 1993-1994 (Box 1)
    - Boland, Eavan, undated (Box 1)
    - Bottoms, David, 1995 (Box 1)
    - Brodsky, Louis Daniel, 1993, 1997 (Box 1)
    - Buckley, Christopher, 1997-1999 (Box 1)
    - Burkhard, Michael, 1992-1993 (Box 1)
    - Carruth, Hayden, 1993 (Box 1)
    - Citino, David, 1993 (Box 1)
    - Clewell, David, 1998-2000 (Box 1)
    - Clifton, Lucille, 1993 (Box 1)
    - Collins, Billy, 1993-1995 (Box 1)
    - Connellan, Leo, 1993-1995 (Box 1)
    - Creeley, Robert, 1993-1997 (Box 1)
    - Dana, Robert, 1997-1998 (Box 1)
    - DeFrees, Madeline, 1999 (Box 1)
    - Doty, Marie, 1995-2000 (Box 1)
    - Dove, Rita, 1993 (Box 1)
    - Dubie, Norman, 1993 (Box 1)
    - Dukes, Carol Muske, 1995 (Box 1)
    - Dunn, Stephen, 1990-1999 (Box 1)
    - Elmslie, Kenword, 1993 (Box 1)
    - Enslin, Theodore, 1992 (Box 1)
    - Eshleman, Clayton, 1993 (Box 1)
    - Ferlinghetti, Lawrence, 1993-1994, undated (Box 1)
    - Fixel, Lawrence, 1992-1995 (Box 1)
    - Forché, Carolyn, 1998 (Box 1)
    - Fulton, Alice, 1997 (Box 1)
    - Gallagher, Tess, 1993-1998 (Box 1)
    - Garris, Mildred, 1993 (Box 1)
    - Green, Stan, 1995 (Box 1)
    - Gregg, Linda, 1995, 1997 (Box 1)
    - Gilbert, Jack, 1995, 1997 (Box 1)
    - Gildner, Gary, 1993-1994 (Box 1)
    - Gioia, Dana, 1995 (Box 1)
    - Giovanni, Nikki, 1993 (Box 1)
    - Glück, Louise, 1993 (Box 1)
    - Grennan, Eamon, 1993-2000 (Box 1)
    - Haas, Robert, 1993 (Box 1)
    - Hall, Donald, 1994-2000; 2 (Box 1)
    - Haines, John, 1995-1998 (Box 1)
    - Hall, Joan Joffe, 2000 (Box 1)
    - Harper, Michael S., 1986-1988 (Box 1)
    - Hathaway, William, 1993 (Box 1)
    - Heaney, Seamus, 1985 (Box 1)
    - Heyen, William, 1994-2000; 2 (Box 1)
    - Hoffman, Daniel, 1993-2001; 2 (Box 1)
    - Hollander, John, 1995 (Box 1)
    - Hongo, Garrett Kaouru, 1995 (Box 1)
    - Ignatow, David, 1993 (Box 1)
    - Jabes, Edmond, 1988, 1991 (Box 1)
    - Justice, Donald, 1993-1997 (Box 1)
    - Kennedy, X. J., 1993 (Box 1)
    - Kherdian, David, 1995, undated (Box 1)
    - Kizer, Carolyn, 1993 (Box 1)
    - Kinnell, Galway, 1986-1999 (Box 1)
    - Knott, Bill, 1998, undated (Box 1)
    - Knudson, Jan, 1995 (Box 1)
    - Koch, Kenneth, 1993 (Box 1)
    - Kumin, Maxine, 1993 (Box 1)
    - Kunitz, Stanley, 1993-1995 (Box 1)
    - Langland, Joseph T., 1995-1999 (Box 1)
    - Laughlin, James, 1987 (Box 1)
    - Levertov, Denise, 1993 (Box 1)
    - Levine, Philip, 1993-1999 (Box 1)
    - Logan, William, 2000 (Box 1)
    - Macklin, Elizabeth, 1995 (Box 1)
    - Merwin, William S., 1997-1999 (Box 1)
    - Muske, Carol, 1995, 1999 (Box 1)
    - Nims, John Frederick, 1994-1999 (Box 1)
    - Olds, Sharon, 1989-1997 (Box 1)
    - Pastan, Linda, 1993-2001 (Box 1)
    - Perlman, John, 2001 (Box 1)
    - Piercy, Marge, 1990-1997 (Box 1)
    - Rakosi, Carl, 1993-1999 (Box 1)
    - Sarton, Mary, 1993-1995 (Box 1)
    - Schreiber, Ilse, 1995 (Box 1)
    - Schulman, Grace, 1995, 1997 (Box 1)
    - Seidman, Hugh, 1995-2001 (Box 1)
    - Simic, Charles, 1993, 1995 (Box 1)
    - Smith, William Jay, 1999-2000 (Box 1)
    - Snodgrass, W. D., 1993-2001 (Box 2)
    - Soto, Gary, 1995 (Box 2)
    - Stern, Gerald, 1993 (Box 2)
    - Strand, Mark, 1993 (Box 2)
    - Snyder, Gary, 1995 (Box 2)
    - Wagoner, David, 1993 (Box 2)
    - Wakoski, Diane, 1993-1998 (Box 2)
    - Wiebe, Dallas, 1990 (Box 2)
    - Wieners, John, 1993 (Box 2)
    - Wilbur, Richard, 1993-2001 (Box 2)
    - Williams, Aubrey L., 1997 (Box 2)
    - Wright, Charles P., 1993 (Box 2)
    - Wright, Franz, 1990 (Box 2)
    - Valentine, Jean, 1997-2000 (Box 2)
    - Zimmer, Paul, 1997-2001 (Box 2)
  - Checks, A-Z, 11 (Box 2)
    Made out to various poets
  - Correspondence
    - Bly, Robert, 1996 (Box 3)
    - Buckley, Christopher, 1996-1997 (Box 3)
    - Collins, Billy, 1996 (Box 3)
    - [Corn], Alfred, 1996 (Box 3)
    - Creeley, Robert, 1997 (Box 3)
    - DeFrees, Madeline, 1997 (Box 3)
    - Espada, Martin, 1996 (Box 3)
    - Ewert, William and Mary, 1996 (Box 3)
    - Fulton, Lice, 1996 (Box 3)
    - Gallagher, Tess, 1996 (Box 3)
    - Gilbert, Jack, 1996-1997 (Box 3)
    - Gioia, Dana, 1995 (Box 3)
    - Grennan, Eamon, 1996 (Box 3)
    - Haines, John, 1996 (Box 3)
    - Hall, Donald, 1996-1997 (Box 3)
    - Heyen, William, 1996 (Box 3)
    - Hoffman, Daniel, 1996 (Box 3)
    - Jama, Stephen, 1997 (Box 3)
    - Kelly, Brigit Pegeen, undated (Box 3)
    - Kherdian, David, 1997 (Box 3)
    - Kinnell, Galway, 1996 (Box 3)
    - Kumin, Maxine, 1996-1997 (Box 3)
    - Langland, Joseph, 1996 (Box 3)
    - Lee, Lee Young, undated (Box 3)
    - Levine, Philip, 1996-1997 (Box 3)
    - Merwin, William S., 1996-1997 (Box 3)
    - Muske, Carol, 1996 (Box 3)
    - Nims, John Frederick, 1996-1997 (Box 3)
    - Pasten, Linda, undated (Box 3)
    - Pierce, Marge, 1996 (Box 3)
    - Rakoski, Carl, 1995-2001 (Box 3)
    - Sirmons, Michael, 1997 (Box 3)
    - Snodgrass, W. D., 1996 (Box 3)
    - Swenson, May (R. Knudson), undated (Box 3)
    - Valentine, Jean, undated (Box 3)
    - Wakoski, Diane, 1996-1997 (Box 3)
    - Wieners, John, 1997 (Box 3)
    - Wilbur, Richard, 1996 (Box 3)
    - Williams, Aubrey, 1997 (Box 3)
    - Zimmer, Paul, 1996 (Box 3)
- October 2002 Acquisition, 1986-2001; 2; 3.21; (4 boxes)
  Conditions Governing Access
  Box 7 (computer disks): Restricted fragile material. Reference copies of electronic files may be requested. Consult Access Services for further information.
  Consists of sales files, invoices, bills, correspondence regarding various sales, and computer disks storing VERSEtility BOOKS catalogs and a print ad copy for Poetry Magazine.
  Former call number: Uncat MSS 376
  - Sales files, 1993-1997; 13 (Box 4)
  - Sales files, 1997-2000; 9 (Box 5)
  - Invoices, 1993, 1999-2001; 3 (Box 5)
  - Bills, 1994-1995; 2 (Box 5)
  - Bills, 1996-1999; 3 (Box 6)
  - Correspondence regarding various sales, 1986-2001; 19 (Box 6)
    Includes letters with John F. Nims and William Jay Smith regarding the sale of their personal libraries.
  - Computer disks, undated; (9 3.5" computer disks)
    Restricted fragile material. Reference copies of electronic files may be requested. Consult Access Services for further information.
    The disks are labeled: CAT A-L; CAT M-L; CAT 20; CAT 21; CAT 26; CAT COVER, B. CAT; WEB 3; and 3d WEB LIST. The disks store VERSEtility BOOKS catalogs and a print ad copy for Poetry Magazine.
    - WEB 3, 2002-ycal-1010-ay-0001; 1 (Box 7)
      Restricted fragile material. Access copies of digital files may be requested. Consult Access Services for further information.
    - B CAT., 2002-ycal-1010-ay-0002; 1 (Box 7)
    - 3d WEB LIST, 2002-ycal-1010-ay-0003; 1 (Box 7)
    - CAT. COVER, 2002-ycal-1010-ay-0004; 1 (Box 7)
    - CAT. A-L, 2002-ycal-1010-ay-0005; 1 (Box 7)
    - CAT. -- M-Z, 2002-ycal-1010-ay-0006; 1 (Box 7)
    - Cat 20, 2002-ycal-1010-ay-0007; 1 (Box 7)
    - CAT 20, 2002-ycal-1010-ay-0008; 1 (Box 7)
    - CAT 21, 2002-ycal-1010-ay-0009; 1 (Box 7)